Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Liane Brandon, New Day Films Co-Founder Files, 1970-2014; 14.0 Linear Feet 24 boxes (mss.); 6 film reels (1 box); 6 optical and video disks; 1 audio CD; 5 digital files (.mp4s, .mov, .iso)
  - Films and Film Project Papers, 1970-2014; 11 Linear Feet 19 boxes (mss.); 6 film reels (1 box); 6 optical and video disks; 5 digital files (.mp4s, .mov, .iso)
    - How to Prevent a Nuclear War (1987), 1979-2004; Total running time: 00:30:00
      - Papers, 1979-2004
        - Production, circa 1983-2004
          - Cast list, production credits, synopses, transcript, film release press and flier, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Film credits list, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Mixing, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Opticals, titles, credits proofs sent to EFX Unlimited, 1987 (Box 5)
            Two sets of film credit proofs removed to oversize boxes.
          - Oversize cue sheets for film editing, 1987 (Box 64)
          - Oversize film credit proofs, 1987 (Box 64)
          - Oversize title and credit proofs, 1987 (Box 65)
          - Stat for crawl, sent to EFX Unlimited, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Transcripts, quotes, scripts, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Negative cutting, release print, and correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
        - Publicity/Press, 1983-2003
          - Cartoon: Nuclear Daze, in support of Brandon's film project, 1983 (Box 5)
          - Articles, clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
            Some newspapers have been removed to oversize box.
          - Photographs of set and cast, black-and-white, circa 1984-1985 (Box 5)
          - Responses to film - letters, cards, and comments, 1984-1989 (Box 5)
            A large file of correspondence and comments in response to the film. Includes a packet of written responses from teachers in Alaska.
          - Oversize clippings, newsletter issues, 1985-2003 (Box 65)
          - Oversize newspapers and clippings, 1987-1988 (Box 65)
          - Articles in magazines, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
          - Gospel concert poster and press release, 1986 June 21 (Box 6)
          - Articles, clippings, 1986-2003 and undated (Box 5)
            Some newspaper clippings and newsletter issues have been removed to oversize box.
          - Press contacts for premiere, 1987 August 01-1987 September 30 (Box 6)
          - Newspaper reviews and announcements, Boston area, 1987 September-November; 12 folders (Box 6)
            Publications, each with their own folders, include Boston Globe, Boston Herald, Boston Magazine, and Hampshire Daily Gazette. Most are clippings, but there are some full issues. There are also photocopied items.
          - Fliers announcing film release, circa 1987 (Box 6)
          - Brochure and endorsements, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
          - Final brochure copy and correspondence with designers, 1988 February (Box 6)
          - Women's Action for Nuclear Disarmament (WAND) Bulletin, and national conference program and materials, 1988 February (Box 6)
          - Nuclear Times advertisement/blurb for Brandon film, 1988 May-June (Box 6)
          - Boston City Council resolution, 1988 June 8 (Box 6)
          - Flier with order form at bottom, circa 1988 (Box 6)
          - Boston Film Critics Award and Boston Globe and Herald articles, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
          - Reviews and mentions, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
        - Screenings, 1986-1991
          - Alaska premiere materials, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
          - Layout and designs for premiere invitation and publicity, 1987 (Box 6)
          - Premiere planning materials, 1987 (Box 6)
          - Fliers for screenings, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
            Three posters were removed to an oversize box.
          - Oversize posters for screenings (Boston area), 1987?-1988; 2 items (Box 65)
          - Oversize poster for Boston Film/Video Foundation screening, 1987? (Box 66)
          - Festival screenings and awards, 1987-1989 (Box 7)
          - American Psychological Association (APA) correspondence, 1987 May (Box 7)
          - Columbus Film Festival, 1987 September-October (Box 7)
          - American Film Festival blue ribbon, 1988 (Box 7)
          - "Meet the Filmmakers" program, Crandall Library, Glens Falls, NY, 1988 (Box 7)
            One small poster removed to oversize box.
          - Poster for screening at Glens Falls, NY, 1988 (Box 65)
          - Peacemakers, International Women's Peace Conference correspondence and newsletter, 1988 February-August (Box 7)
          - Various screening materials, 1987-1991 (Box 7)
            Two screening posters have been removed to an oversize box.
          - Screenings: Oversize posters, circa 1985, 1987 (Box 65)
    - Not So Young Now as Then (1973), 1972-1975
      Series contains papers related to the film project, arranged in these subgroups: Financials, Production, Publicity/Press, and Screenings. Currently no film elements are available.
      This short film's setting is the filmmaker's 15th high school reunion. Through the reunion scenes, interviews, and music, the film explores the men and women's relationships, their hopes, dreams, and realities, and the social roles they take on after graduating from high school in 1957.
      - Financials: Expenses, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
      - Production: Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
      - Production: Notes, shot lists, soundtrack log, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Publicity/Press: Reviews, press release layouts, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
      - Screenings: Festivals, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
        Large poster removed to oversize box.
      - Sinking Creek film festival and competition, oversize poster, 1974 June (Box 66)
    - Once Upon A Choice (1980), 1975-2011; Total running time: 00:15:00
      Series contains analog film elements and a digital version of the film. Papers related to the film project are arranged in these subgroups: Financials, Production, Publicity/Press, and Screenings. Within subgroups, folders are arranged chronologically.
      Once Upon A Choice is a humorous, original fairy tale in which an unconventional princess faces the conventional dilemma of deciding which prince to marry. Instead, she decides to choose her own fate, deciding for herself what it means to live "happily ever after" - and raising important questions about marriage, independence and responsibility.
      - Audiovisual Resources, 1980
        - Once Upon a Choice, dvd image, 1980 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-OD, Object RL10180-DVD-0005.iso)
        - Once Upon a Choice, 1980; 00:15:00 (Box AV-07, Video-disc RL10180-DVD-0005)
      - Papers, 1975-1992, 2011
        - Financials: Expenses, film lab invoices, 1975, 1983-1984, 2011 (Box 7)
        - Financials: American Association of University Woman (AAUW) grant information and correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
        - Financials: Massachusetts Foundation for Humanities and Public Policy grant file, 1975-1983 (Box 7)
          Includes proposal, correspondence, and final report by Liane Brandon.
        - Production: Costumes and props documents, 1975 (Box 8)
        - Production: Notes, contracts, measurements, phone numbers, 1975 (Box 8)
        - Production: Set photographs, prop lists, shooting schedule lists, 1975 (Box 8)
        - Production: Shot logs and key numbers, camera reports, 1975 (Box 8)
        - Production: Scripts by Liane Brandon and Debra Franco, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
        - Production: Release forms from actors (1975) and panelists (1980), 1975, 1980 (Box 8)
        - Production: Optical and title information, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
        - Production: Cue sheets, 1980 October (Box 8)
        - Production: Narration scripts, credits sheet, dialogue transcript, and music notes, 1980 (Box 8)
        - Publicity/Press: Brochure layout materials, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
        - Publicity/Press: Screenings and speaking engagements, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
        - Publicity/Press: News articles, 1980-1982 (Box 8)
          Some materials removed to oversize box.
        - Publicity/Press: Large film festival poster with screening of Once Upon a Choice at Coolidge Corner 2 theater, Brookline, Massachusetts, early 1980s? (Box 65)
        - Publicity/Press: Three oversize news clippings (photocopies) and one poster/flier from Massachusetts Foundation for Humanities and Public Policy with mention of Once Upon A Choice, 1980-1983 (Box 65)
        - Publicity/Press: Clippings, 1980-1983 (Box 8)
        - Publicity/Press: Brochures, printing invoices and information, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
        - Publicity/Press: Press releases, 1983 (Box 9)
        - Screenings: Various materials and list of awards, 1980-1992 (Box 9)
          Includes a list of awards and featured screenings.
        - Screenings: Awards, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
        - Screenings: TV (U.S. and Europe), Charles Schuerhoff/CAS, and Independent Cinema Artists and Producers (ICAP) cable screening, 1981-1990 (Box 9)
          Includes correspondence, publicity, and contracts.
        - Screenings: U.S. Department of Education, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
    - Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am (1970), 1970-1978
      This series contains only papers related to the film Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am. There are also references to the film, which was shown frequently in women's film festivals, in clippings and fliers in other series, chiefly in the Liane Brandon/Films/General series, and in New Day Films Cooperative Files publicity materials.
      This very early feminist film is not a glowing image of motherhood. It was shot in 1969 when the filmmaker was a member of Bread and Roses, one of the first Second Wave Women's Liberation groups. The film is a brief succinct study of the conflict felt by a young housewife who dreams of the career she could have had. The camera's methodical exploration of the woman's pensive face and the confined environment of her kitchen as she washes dishes, prepares a meal, feeds her baby, and cleans up again - underlines her hesitating contemplation of her life and her feelings as a wife and mother, the reaction of her husband to her emerging feelings, the sensation that people think of her only as her husband's wife or baby's mother, and the thought of what she will be like in 10 years. This was one of the very early "consciousness raising" films of the growing Women's Movement.
      - Audiovisual Resources, 1970
        - Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am, digital movie, 1970 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0001_u, Video-file Sometimes_I_Wonder.mov)
      - Papers, 1970s
        - Production: photo stills from film; artist's statement, invoices, 1970 and undated (Box 9)
          A clipping and a poster were removed to oversize box.
        - Publicity: Who moves the movement?, news article with paragraph about screening of Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am at Bread and Roses meeting, 1970 August 18 (Box 65)
          The article was written by Nancy Williamson, and profiled Boston area women's organizations, including Bread and Roses.
        - Publicity: Oversize poster/mailer from Women's Film Co-op, Northampton, Mass., with list of films for rent, including Sometimes I Wonder Who I Am, 1970s? (Box 65)
        - Publicity: correspondence and publicity, WGBH Boston and others, 1970-1978 (Box 9)
    - Liane Brandon Films: General Files, 1970-2013; .8 Linear Feet
      Arranged in chronological order, these folders document Brandon's career and activities as a filmmaker. Topics include items relating to lawsuits by New Day Films, largely handled by Brandon; articles about Brandon and interviews with her; a set of photographic prints and digital images from her films; and film screenings and other publicity. There is a large group of clippings and articles documenting her long career, usually in newspaper format and often including publicity shots. Some are photocopies.
      Other materials specific to each of her film titles are found in the Liane Brandon Films Subseries. Additional materials concerning New Day Films lawsuits can be found in the Amalie R. Rothschild New Day Cooperative files subseries (correspondence as well as oversize news clippings file), and in the New Day Cooperative Films records series, Topical subseries under "Lawsuits."
      - Production: Copyright documentation for lawsuits and general resources, 1970-2002 (Box 9)
      - Production: Lab and storage invoices, correspondence, 1975-1997 (Box 9)
      - Production: Assorted invoices for courier services and other activities, 1991 (Box 9)
      - Publicity/Press: Still photographs of Liane Brandon, Cambridge, Mass., black-and-white, 1971 (Box 9)
        Two 5x7 inch black-and-white prints of Liane Brandon, seated, with a cat on her lap, and standing, working over a desk.
      - Publicity/Press: Articles, press mentions, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
      - Publicity/Press: Clippings, 1971-1979 (Box 9)
      - Publicity/Press: Digitized still images from Liane Brandon's films, 1971-2012; 420 MB (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-OD, Object RL10180-OP-0003.iso)
      - Publicity/Press: Digitized still images from Liane Brandon's films, 1971-2012; 420 MB (Box AV-07, Optical-disc RL10180-OP-0003)
      - Oversize clippings and newsletters with articles about Liane Brandon's career and filmmaking, 1972-1980; 2 folders (Box 65)
        These items were part of a series of loose publicity materials. Many are illustrated with portraits of Brandon.
      - Publicity/Press: Clippings and article extracts about New Day Films, 1972-1981 (Box 9)
        Chiefly from the 1970s, these news clippings and articles contain much information about the beginnings of New Day Films, and feature quotes from core members about the mission of the cooperative as an independent distributor.
      - Publicity/Press: Film catalogs and other listings with New Day films, 1973-1977 (Box 9)
      - Publicity/Press: Interviews, 1973-2004 (Box 10)
        Includes an interview in The Second Wave magazine, and a 2004 interview by Nat Segaloff in which Brandon reminisces about her work and "social issue" films.
      - Publicity/Press: Film fliers, circa 1973-2000s (Box 10)
        Includes a "Films by Liane Brandon" flier and mock-up, circa 1973.
      - Publicity/Press: Articles, press mentions, 1974-1978 (Box 10)
      - Publicity/Press: Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 10)
      - Publicity/Press: Articles, press mentions, 1980-1991 (Box 10)
      - Publicity/Press: Teaching awards, 1984-1985 (Box 10)
      - Publicity/Press: "A Tribute to New Day Films," Nebraska Press event, 1990 (Box 10)
        Program took place at the Sheldon Film Theater, Lincoln, Nebraska. Includes programs, fliers, news clippings.
      - Publicity/Press: Oversize news clippings, Boston area, 1999-2011 (Box 64)
      - Publicity/Press: Oversize news articles and interview, 2000, 2008 (Box 64)
      - Screenings, 1972-2013 (Box 10)
        Materials include publicity such as announcements, invitations, programs, guest lists, and many fliers, as well as some correspondence and planning notes. Screenings in other countries include a women's film festival in Paris and one in Canada. Recent screenings include Boston University and Museum of Modern Art in New York. One small poster was removed to oversize box.
      - Screenings: Oversize news articles on Museum of Modern Art (MOMA) screening of Brandon's films, 2010 (Box 66)
    - Liane Brandon Films: Sales and Rentals, 1971-1980; 4.2 Linear Feet 9 boxes
      Large group of invoices and other receipts from sales and rentals of Liane Brandon's as well as New Day films (the first decade), documenting the wide variety and demographics of individuals, institutions, and organizations acquiring and viewing Brandon's films. There are quite a few pieces of correspondence, mostly referring to account or delivery issues, but sometimes offering viewpoints on the films themselves. Most titles are transcribed from originals.
      - Rental receipts and letters, 1971-1973 (Box 11)
        The great majority of receipts and invoices are for Brandon's Anything You Want to Be, but there are also sales and rentals for Betty Tells Her Story. Some folders contain "multiple sales" of New Day titles. The distributor for these requests is almost exclusively Transit Media (TM), with whom New Day worked.
      - Sales billing: unpaid accounts, circa 1972 (Box 11)
      - Rental preview and rental slips: cancellations, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
      - Film Bureau rentals: receipts, orders, vouchers, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
      - New Day sales lists, circa 1972-1973 (Box 11)
        Five sales lists of purchaser's names and addresses. Four lists are specific to a co-founder: Liane Brandon, Jim Klein and Julia Reinhardt, and Amalie Rothschild (two lists representing It Happens to Us and Woo Whoo May Wilson). The fifth is for Joyce Chopra's Joyce at 34 (1972). The lists document the types of institutions, organizations, and individuals purchasing these early titles.
      - Multiple films sold from Brandon's residence, 1972-1976 (Box 11)
      - Film Bureau invoices, monthly paid and old, 1973-1974 (Box 11)
      - Multiple sales - done, 1974-1976 (Box 11)
      - Multiple sales - invoiced and paid, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Multiple sales - paid, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Sales receipts and letters from libraries, 1971-1973; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Sales receipts for Anything You Want to Be, sold from Brandon's residence, 1973-1975; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Sales receipts from Transit Media for Anything You Want to Be, 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Sales receipts from Transit Media for Anything You Want to Be, 1974-1976; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Sales receipts from Transit Media for Anything You Want to Be, 1976-1977; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Sales receipts from Transit Media for Anything You Want to Be, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Sales receipts from Transit Media for Anything You Want to Be, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Rental receipts for Anything You Want to Be, 1973-1974; 8 folders (Box 15)
      - Rental receipts for Anything You Want to Be, 1974; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Rental receipts for Anything You Want to Be, 1974-1975; 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Rental receipts for Anything You Want to Be, 1975-1976; 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Cardfile of sales lists, rental and sales records, and other transactions and notes, 1973-1976 (Box 19)
        Box contains New Day's index card system used in the first years of its founding. Organized by transaction function; includes section on paid as well as unpaid accounts. Sales lists contain names and addresses of individuals, institutions, and organizations who previewed or bought New Day films.
  - Women's Liberation Radio Documentary (audio recording), 1970
    - Women's Liberation radio documentary, digital access copy, 1970; 00:28:00 (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-OD, Object RL10180-CD-0001.iso)
    - Women's Liberation radio documentary, optical disc, 1970; 00:28:00 (Box AV-07, Audio-cd RL10180-CD-0001)
  - Brandon: Correspondence Files, 1971-1987; .75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
    Folders contain incoming and outgoing correspondence, often with supporting materials or attachments, arranged in chronological order. Contents cover a range of topics associated with Brandon's career and activities as a feminist filmmaker, writer and activist. Other correspondence is found in Brandon's New Day co-op files, as well as in co-founder Amalie Rothschild's papers. Related correspondence from later decades is found throughout the rest of the collection.
    - Correspondence with authors, publishers, editors, 1971-1984 (Box 20)
      A number of these items, almost all incoming, are requests to Brandon from authors or editors of book-length works, often on women in film. Includes a few rough drafts of articles.
    - Radio and television contracts, correspondence, screenings, appearances, 1971-1987 (Box 20)
    - Contract and correspondence, Aetna Equal Opportunity Program, 1972-1973 (Box 20)
      Includes Aetna's "Helping By Doing" social responsibility report.
    - International film seminars, Flaherty seminar (1972) and related correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 20)
      International Women and Film, St. Lawrence Centre, Canada; Flaherty Film Seminar, Lakeville, Connecticut.
    - Contracts and correspondence, Canadian Film Cooperative, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
    - Contracts and (non)contracts, 1972-1979 (Box 20)
    - New Day Films: non-routine correspondence, requests, 1972-1980 and undated (Box 21)
    - Conferences: correspondence, programs, flyers, 1973-1979 (Box 21)
    - Contracts and correspondence, Leonard Henny, Films for Social Change in Europe (Holland, University of Utrecht), 1973-1975 (Box 21)
      Includes Liane Brandon's paper "Film technology and revolutionary social change," for the International Film Conference on Alternative Media held in Montreal, Canada, June 1974, and for the World Congress of Sociology, held in Toronto, Canada, August 1974.
    - Contracts and other business, American Federation of Arts, Northampton Film Cooperative, West Hartford Schools, 1974-1977 (Box 21)
    - Letter to the editor, 1975 (Box 21)
      Letter to the editor published in the March 1975 edition of Media and Methods, authored by Liane Brandon. Critiques the journal's practice of omitting filmmakers' names when writing about their film.
  - Brandon: New Day Films Cooperative Files, 1971-1986, 2012; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes
    Files in this series were maintained by co-founder Liane Brandon and are arranged chronologically. Some of the earliest materials documenting the formation and operation of the New Day Films Cooperative are found here, beginning with planning notes from 1971.
    Files contain incoming and outgoing correspondence, planning notes, financial records, some meeting notes, and graphics layouts for early New Day catalogs. The final dates in the 1980s mark the transition that came with hiring a consultancy firm and the centralization of the file management for the cooperative. The latest date in the series is a 2012 announcement by Liane Brandon related to the renewal of New Day Films' registered trademark/service mark.
    Documentation concerning important copyright and plagiarism lawsuits pursued by Brandon and others on behalf of New Day, critical to the independent filmmaking enterprise, is chiefly found in the film series for Anything You Want To Be and in the main New Day Films Cooperative/Topical Files series.
    Materials in this series sometimes overlap with content in the smaller series of similar files kept by co-founder Amalie Rothschild; there is also overlap with content in the main New Day Films Cooperative Files series.
    - First New Day Films cooperative planning, early correspondence, agreements, 1971-1972 (Box 22)
    - New Day Films correspondence and third meeting, 1972 September-1973 June (Box 22)
    - Film Bureau correspondence and some preview referrals, 1972 October-1973 June (Box 22)
    - Second mailing expenses, new mailing list, graphic design invoice, 1972 (Box 22)
    - Film Bureau bills and initial New Day costs, 1972-1973 (Box 22)
    - Two film festivals showing New Day founders' films, 1972-1973 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, including leaving Film Bureau, 1973 April-1974 November (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, 1974 December-1975 December (Box 22)
    - Old meeting notes and decisions, 1975 November-1979 December (Box 22)
      Includes photocopy of original 1975-1976 New York Radical Feminists' "Introduction to Consciousness Raising" (6 pages).
    - Mailing lists and some labels, circa mid-1970s (Box 22)
    - Correspondence and flyers, 1976 January-1976 December (Box 22)
    - New Day Films 1976 catalog: copy, layouts, mock-ups, prices, 1975-1978 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, 1977 January-1977 December (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, 1978 January-1978 December (Box 23)